Robert Garrett Collection of Ethiopic Magic Scrolls, 1700-1900: Finding Aid C0744.04
Manuscripts Division
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 57, 1800-1899; 57; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a reasonable hand (3-4mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow. 3 talismanic drawings. Compare scroll no. 111, which appears to have been drawn by the same ar
  - Prayer for the Binding of Demons and Devils, Barya and Légéwon, Tegrida and Buda ... etc, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for the Drowning of Demons and Devils, Barya and Légéwon ... etc, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for the Drowning of Demons and Devils, etc, 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 58, 1830-1870; 58; 6 short pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a medium hand (3-5mm). 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 2)
  Derivative of the eight-pointed star design with central face; four arms form a cross each of which terminates in a pair of curved lobes. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Grid of 9 squares with transverse cross designs, alternately with central faces or protective eye-motifs. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Eight-pointed star design with central face. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Additionally, there is a series of three decorative bands at the top of the scroll.
  Owner: the original owner's name has been erased and variously replaced with those of Sebhat Lä'ab, Kidanä Maryam, and As'qa Rufa'él (all m.)
  - Prayer for Exorcising Demons, as Well as Barya, Blacksmiths and Buda, "by the Secret Names of Thy Word, Jesus Christ, and by the Sword of Michael", mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Binding Barya, Légéwon and Evil Demons, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Sickness Caused by Barya and Blacksmiths, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against "The Black Barya Which Breaks the Bones and Strangles the Neck", mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against (Chest) Pain, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Barya, Légéwon, Nägärgar and Demons, mid 19th century; 1 item
    Untitled. Opens with the beginning of the Gospel of John.
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 59, 1800-1850; 59; 3 pieces of coarse parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics (now partly faded) in an uneven and mediocre hand (3-5mm). 4 talismanic drawings. (Box 2)
  Eight-pointed star design with central face. (In ink with red color, now faded.)
  Another eight-pointed star design with central face. (In ink with some red color and a faded yellow wash.)
  A further eight-pointed star design with a central face. (In ink with some red color and traces of yellow wash.)
  Owners: the original owners' names occur as Wäldä Sämu'él (m.) and Wälättä — (f.), the latter being replaced by that of Wälättä Kidan (f.)
  - Prayer for Salvation from Werzelya, Jaundice (Aynä Wärq), Shotälay, Cannibals, Vampires and Casters of spells; Prayer Against Miscarriage Caused by Werzelya, early/mid 19th century; 1 item
    In continuo. Untitled.
  - Prayer of Solomon for Cursing Demons, early/mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Driving Away Demons, Barya, Däsk, Gudalé, the Noontide Demon, Sorcerers ... etc, early/mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Devils, Death, Sheol and Sin, early/mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Demons and Sorcerers, early/mid 19th century; 1 item
    Untitled. Contains the beginning of the Gospel of John.
  - Prayer against Colic and (Chest) Pain, early/mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Anathematizing Satan and His Demons in the Name of the Trinity, early/mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 60, 1750-1799; 60; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. 2 cols., written in black with rubrics in an elegant and well-formed hand (4mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow, and separated by a central margin decorated with alternate small transverse cross and lobed lozenge designs in red and brown. The rubrics do not necessarily indicate sections but are distributed to form horizontal bands across the scroll (s. also no. 68.) 3 finely executed talismanic drawings, and a number of talismanic figures inserted within the text. (Box 2)
  An angelic or seraphic figure within a lozenge shape, framed by flowing, foliate lines. (In ink with black, red and yellow color.)
  A derivative of the eight-pointed star motif (?) but without a central face, forming an intricate pattern of transverse crosses and lobed figures. (In ink with black, red and yellow color.)
  Another abstract design which may derive from the eight-pointed star or flanged cross design, with checkerboard infill at the four corners. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  There are additionally 4 grids of letters placed within the text.
  Owner: Wäldä Mika'él (m.)
  - Series of Prayers for "Drowning" Barya, Légéwon, Buda, Qumäñña, Colic, Rheumatism, (Chest) Pain, Mech, Gusemt, Typhoid, Fever, Zar, Tegrida and All Creeping Things; Also for Binding the Demons of the Days of the Week, Beginning With Sunday, According to "Alexander, King of the Sea and the Dry Land", mid/late 18th century; 1 item The prayers run in col. 1 down to drawing 1 and then move to col. 2, and then back to col. 1
  - Prayers against the Evil Eye, Jaundice [aynä wärq], and Nedra, mid/late 18th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Banishing Evil Spirits, mid/late 18th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Banishing Buda and Qumäñña, mid/late 18th century; 1 item
    Untitled. Concludes with a sälam (hymn of salutation) to Phanuel.
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 61, 1870-1899; 61; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. The top of the scroll is badly creased. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in an untidy and cramped hand (3-4mm). 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 2)
  [damaged] Grid of 9 squares with various designs. (In ink with bright blue, red and black color.)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with bright blue, vermilion red and black color.)
  Sketch of an ornate cross. (In ink without color.)
  Owner: Wälättä Mika'él (f.)
  - Prayer against Foul Légéwon; Prayer Against Sickness Caused by Légéwon and Barya, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Foul Légéwon, late 19th century; 1 item
  - A Prayer against Colic; Sälam (Hymn Of Salutation) to Phanuel, late 19th century; 1 item
  - A Prayer against Légéwon "Who Cuts the Hearts of Men", late 19th century; 1 item
  - Sälam to Phanuel, late 19th century; 1 item
  - A Prayer against Blacksmiths (Bä'entä Zänäha[b]t [sic]), late 19th century; 1 item
  - Series of Prayers against Hemorrhage and for Successful Pregnancy, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Binding Demons, late 19th century; 1 item
    Untitled. Incorporates the beginning of the Gospel of John.
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 62, 1870-1930; 62; 4 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics (in magenta ink) in 2 different hands, one somewhat uneven, (3-4mm), framed between a linear border with traces of yellow color. 2 talismanic drawings and 1 band of decoration. The text beginning on the second piece of the scroll appears to have belonged originally to another scroll. (Box 2)
  Sketch of a hand cross. (In ink without color.)
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Barya and Légéwon, Incorporating the Text Known as the Net of Solomon, circa 1870-1930; 1 item
  - Prayer for Blood Clotting (Arge'a Däm) and for "Strengthening Pregnancy", circa 1870-1930; 1 item
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage, circa 1870-1930; 1 item
    Beginning in abrupto.
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage, circa 1870-1930; 1 item
  - Prayer for the Binding of Demons and Devils, circa 1870-1930; 1 item
  - Prayer against Shotälay and Barya "Who Kills Infants," Incorporating the Legend of Susenyos "Son of Susi P'ét'ros [sic]." Sälam (Hymn of Salutation) to Susenyos "Son of P'ét'ros Susi", circa 1870-1930; 1 item
  - Prayer for the Undoing of Spells, circa 1870-1930; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 63, 1830-1870; 63; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. There is rodent damage to some of the edges. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a somewhat untutored hand (4-5mm), framed between a linear border drawn with a pair of zigzag lines and colored yellow. 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 2)
  Guardian angel with a drawn sword (roughly executed). (In ink with red and yellow wash.)
  At the foot of the drawing is a pen trial in an uneducated hand. 2 eight-pointed star designs with central faces, one above the other. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Another 2 eight-pointed star designs with central faces, one above the other. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Owners: Wälättä Gäbre'él (f.) and her husband Ar'aya Sellasé.
  - Prayer for the Undoing of Spells (Mäftehé Seray), Classified According to the Occupation, Religious Affiliation and Home Region of the Caster, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for the Binding of Demons, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Légéwon, Beginning With an Extract from the Gospel of Luke, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for the Binding of Demons, mid 19th century; 1 item
    Begina with the opening of the Gospel of John.
  - Prayer against Foul Légéwon, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Buda and Blacksmiths, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against (Chest) Pain, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye Emanating from "Black and Red [People]", mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Barya, Hemorrhage and Shotälay, mid 19th century; 1 item
    Concludes with the story of the woman who had an issue of blood from the Gospel of Mark.
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 64, 1800-1850; 64; 2 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a large and mediocre hand (6mm). 4 talismanic drawings. The hand and drawings are nearly identical to those of scroll no. 75. (Box 2)
  Protective figure formed of a face atop a decorated triangle. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  A similar protective figure to no. 1., but with a square face. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  A similar protective figure to no. 1. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  An ornamented cross surrounded by four circles. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Owner: Kidanä Wäld (m.)
  - Prayer for the Binding of Demons, Beginning With a Sälam (Hymn of Salutation) to Phanuel, early/mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Sickness Caused by Barya and Légéwon, Gudalé And T'äfänt, Mäggañña and Gusemt ... etc, early/mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 65, 1800-1850; 65; incomplete]A single piece of parchment, forming the bottom part of a scroll, the rest now missing. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a reasonable hand (4mm), framed within a linear border decorated with chevrons with yellow color. 2 talismanic drawings. (Box 2)
  Cross with rays extending from between the arms. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  "Sun face" with 18 arms radiating from the central face. (In ink with black and yellow color.)
  Owner: Gäbrä Heywät (m.)
  - Probably the Temhertä Hebu'at or Doctrina Arcanorum, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
    End portion of text, beginning in abrupto.
  - Prayer for "Binding" the Fiery Evil Eye (Aynä t'äbaye' Esatawi), circa 1800-1850; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 66, 1800-1899; 66; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. The top of the scroll is missing and the edges are slightly damaged and the text is blotted. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in an untidy hand (4-5mm), framed between a linear border with zigzag infill colored in blue-grey and red. 4 talismanic drawings. (Box 2)
  Grid of 6 (originally 9) squares with a face in the center, to the right, the left and below, forming (originally) a cruciform shape. (In ink with red and blue-grey color, now much faded and stained.)
  Grid of 9 squares with a face at the center and protective eye-motifs in the four corner squares. (In ink with red, blue-grey and yellow color.)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with red, blue-grey and yellow color.)
  Rosette or lobed cruciform design. (In ink with red, blue-grey and yellow color.)
  Owner: the original female owner's name has been erased and replaced with that of Wälättä Rufa'él.
  - Prayer and Legend of Susenyos for the Protection of Infants and Their Mothers, 19th century; 1 item
    Concludes with a prayer against sickness, demons, colic, rheumatism, the evil eye, (chest) pain, zar, fever ... etc.
  - Prayer against Shotolay [sic], 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for the Undoing of Spells, Classified in Part According to the Regional Origin of the Caster, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Sorcery; Brief Prayer against Hemorrhage and Colic, 19th century; 1 item
    In continuo. First prayer opens with the story of the Gadarene Swine taken from the Gospel of Matthew.
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 67, 1800-1850; 67; 2 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a bold but mediocre hand (4-5mm), framed between a zigzag border in black. 4 talismanic drawings. In addition, there are a number of fine sketches (in ink and pencil) on the obverse of the scroll. (Box 2)
  Eight-pointed star design with central face. (In ink with red-brown, yellow and dark blue-grey color.)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with black, red and yellow color.) Across the body of the figure is written 'Michael the archangel' (Mika'él liqämäla'e[kt]).
  Decorated cross design with a central face (a cherub ?); four arms (top, bottom, left and right), from which pairs of curved lines extend, terminate in human faces. (In ink with red-brown, yellow and dark blue-grey color.)
  Series of 3 crosses in the shape of hand crosses with schematic figures of the sun and moon below. The final text extends across the top of the figure, and below is written "for there is nothing impossible to God." On the back of the scroll is a series of sketches (in ink or in pencil): human faces, heads of cockerels, vines (haräg), lions, and a regal figure, all in a considerably more sophisticated hand than the talismanic drawings.
  Owner: Kokäbä Läda (m.); the two female names Wälättä Maryam and Amätä Mika'él have also been added at the bottom of the scroll.
  - Prayer for Banishing Evil Spirits, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
    Untitled. Concluding with a prayer for abjuring satan by the power of the Trinity.
  - Prayer against Sickness Caused by Barya and Foul and Accursed Légéwon (Rekus wäregum.), as Well as against Various Other Spirits and Ailments; Closing With a Sälam (Hymn of Salutation) to Phanuel, circa 1800-1850; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 68, 1700-1799; 68; 4 pieces of parchment sewn together; the top of the scroll appears to be missing, and there is damage to the edges and other parts of the scroll. 2 cols., written in black with rubrics (some now faded and illegible) in a small, neat hand (2-3mm), framed between a linear border colored red and separated by a plain central margin colored either red or yellow. The rubrics do not necessarily introduce a new section, but are mostly placed to form bands across the scroll (s. also no. 60.) 4 talismanic drawings. (Box 2)
  Circle with central face surrounded by a ring of smaller faces, with alternating lobes with eye-motifs and crosses radiating from the circle. (In ink with red, brown, perhaps originally green, and yellow color, now very much faded.) Around the figure is repeatedly written the name, Wälättä Gärima.
  A similar design but with a single face at the centre and just four arms in the form of human figures radiating from the circle, the whole enclosed within a larger circle from which a further four inverted faces protrude. (In ink with red, yellow and brown, perhaps originally green, color.) Again the name Wälättä Gärima has been written on the design. Lozenge with a human face at the center from which four further lozenges extend.
  There is a small human figure below the main design and three other decorative motifs either side and above. (In ink with red, yellow and brown, perhaps originally green, color.) Again the name Wälättä Gärima has been written on the design.
  Cross with a central face set within a circle from which four protective eye-motifs extend. (In ink with red, yellow and, perhaps originally green, color.) The names of Abreha S'eyon and Wälättä Gärima have been written across the top of the drawing.
  Owner: the original owner's name has been erased and replaced with those of Wälättä Gärima (f.) and Abreha S'eyon.
  - Prayer(s) for Undoing spells, 18th century; 1 item
    Opening rubrics are now illegible.. The Text Continues With Various Refinements of Types of Spell and Spell-Caster Across Both Columns to Below Drawing No 4.
  - Prayer for Undoing Spells, 18th century; 1 item right-hand col., below drawing 4
    NB unusually for a magic scroll there is an indication in the text of dating: at the very bottom of the scroll, in the left-hand col., is written, '... of our bishop Abba Yohannes and the blessing of our king Iyyasu.' There were three kings called Iyyasu who reigned during the 18th cent.: Iyyasu I (r. 1682-1706), Iyyasu II (r. 1730-55), and Iyyasu III (1784-88). The hand and style of the drawings mitigates against an early 18th cent. date.
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 69, 1800-1899; 69; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together. The top of the scroll has been cut away. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in moderate hand (4-5mm). 3 talismanic drawings, the top one of which is now mostly missing. (Box 2)
  [mostly missing] The foot of a decorated cross.
  Decorated cruciform design. (In ink with some red color.)
  Grid of squares with intricate decorative infill. (In ink with some red and possibly yellow color, now much faded.)
  Owner: S'egé Hanna (f.)
  - Prayer for the Protection of Infants, etc, 19th century; 1 item
    Includes the legend of Susenyos,
  - Prayer against Barya and Shotälay, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Foul Légéwon "Who Cuts the Hearts of Men", 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Tägrida [sic]. Prayer against (Chest) Pain, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Däsk, Gudalé, T'äfänt, Marit, Barya, Légéwon ... etc, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye of Nädéra [sic], 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 70, 1770-1799; 70; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together; the top of the scroll has been cut away. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in possibly two different hands: a small, moderate hand (2-3mm) and a larger hand (3-4mm), framed within a double linear border colored yellow. 3 finely executed talismanic drawings, the top one now partly lost. (Box 2)
  [partly missing] A decorated cross design with a central face and eye-motifs at the end of the arms. (In ink red and yellow color.)
  [top] 6 seated human figures in two rows of three, with hand crosses between the uppermost three; [bottom] a regal figure holding a sword, with two birds and a sun above. (In ink with black, red and yellow color.)
  There are traces of a few sketches on the obverse of the scroll.
  Owner: the original owner's name has been erased and replaced with that of Wälättä Haymanot (f.)
  - The Text Known as the Net of Solomon [Märbäbtä Sälomon], late 18th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Undoing Spells [mäftehé seray]. Prayer against Colic. Prayer against (Chest) Pain and Headache (?), late 18th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against (Chest) Pain, Colic, Rheumatism, and Mäggañña, Incorporating a Sälam (Hymn of Salutation) to Phanuel, late 18th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for Binding Demons, late 18th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 71, 1870-1899; 71; 3 pieces of parchment sewn together, with a small skin tying strap at the top. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a neat hand (3-4mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow. 3 talismanic drawings. (Box 2)
  Lozenge with transverse cross formed of lobed arms ending in florettes. (In ink with yellow, dark blue and pale purple color.)
  Grid of 9 squares with alternate face and transverse cross designs. (In ink with green, blue and pale purple color.)
  Eight-pointed star design with central face. (In ink with blue, yellow, green and purple color.)
  - Prayer and Legend of Susenyos, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer for the Binding of Demons, Barya and Légéwon, late 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye, late 19th century; 1 item
    Contains a story of Jesus and the Disciples and the witch they encountered by the Sea of Galilee.
  - Prayer for Undoing Spells [mäftehé seray], late 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 72, 1830-1870; 72; 2 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a somewhat uneven hand (2-4mm), framed within a linear border with zigzag decoration colored yellow. 3 talismanic drawings. Preserved in a leather cylinder pouch, only one half of which now remains. (Box 2)
  Guardian angel with drawn sword. (In ink with pale red and yellow wash.)
  Cross with central face and decorated arms, set between latticework bands. (In ink with pale red and yellow wash.)
  Hand cross with 2 seraphim either side. (In ink with pale red and yellow wash.)
  Owner: Wälättä Egzi'abehér (f.)
  - Prayer and Legend of Susenyos, mid 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Colic, mid 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 73, 19th century; 73; 1 box 3 pieces of parchment sewn together; there is some tearing in two places. The scroll is now rolled from the top. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a reasonable hand (4mm), framed within a linear border colored yellow. 1 talismanic drawing. Preserved within a leather cylinder pouch. 1070 x 45-50mm (Box 2)
  Contains in continuo: Prayer against the evil eye, barya and légéwon, zar and nägärgar, dedeq and the Noontide Demon ... etc.; prayer against (chest) pain and rheumatism. First prayer contains the secret names of Solomon (asmatä Sälomon)
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 74, 1800-1899; 74; incomplete]A single piece of parchment, forming the bottom portion of a scroll, now rolled from the top. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a mediocre hand (3mm), framed within a linear border showing traces of yellow wash. 1 talismanic drawing. (Box 2)
  Drawing: Sketch of a rosette. (In ink with some red color.)
  Owner: the original owner's name has been overwritten variously by that of Amätä Maryam and Amätä Mädhen (both f.)
  - Prayer against the Evil Eye [of] Barya, Aynä T'ela and Aynä Wärq (Jaundice ?), 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Sickness Caused by Mäggañña, Shotälay, Barya and Légéwon, as Well as Headache, Colic, and Rheumatism, 19th century; 1 item
  - Prayer against Hemorrhage and Shotälay, 19th century; 1 item
- Garrett Ethiopic Magic Scroll No. 75, 1800-1850; 75; 2 pieces of parchment sewn together. 1 col., written in black with rubrics in a mediocre hand (4-5mm), framed between a zigzag border with traces of yellow color. 4 talismanic drawings. Preserved in a leather cylinder pouch, only one half of which now remains. The hand and drawings are nearly identical to those of scroll no. 64. (Box 2)
  An identical protective figure to no. 1. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  An identical protective figure to nos. 1 and 2. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Group of 3 crosses. (In ink with red and yellow color.)
  Owner: the original owner's name, Wälättä Maryam (f.), has been overwritten by that of Ness'eha Dengel.
  - Prayer and Legend of Susenyos, early/mid 19th century; 1 item